<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reports on luis angel ortega</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/reports/</link>
    <description>Recent  Reports on luis angel ortega</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>hey@luisangel.me (Luis Angel Ortega)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>hey@luisangel.me (Luis Angel Ortega)</webMaster>
    <copyright>2025 Luis Angel Ortega Holguin All rights reserved</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 17:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/reports/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Report: Proyecto Hail Mary by Andy Weir</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/02/05/project-hail-mary/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>hey@luisangel.me (Luis Angel Ortega)</author>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/post/2025/02/05/project-hail-mary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some time ago, I finished &lt;em&gt;Project Hail Mary&lt;/em&gt; by Andy Weir, and I felt like writing about it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The premise is simple: a man wakes up on a spaceship with no memory of who he is or what he’s doing there. He’s alone, his crewmates are dead, and little by little, he realizes that his mission is to save humanity. The story follows a progressive discovery format, where both the character and the reader figure things out together. Amnesia as a narrative device can be a cliché if used poorly, but here it works because it gives the story a really engaging pace.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One thing I really liked is that the protagonist isn’t your typical sci-fi hero. He’s not the brave, perfect astronaut who already knows everything. He’s just a regular guy facing an extraordinary situation with the only thing he has—his scientific knowledge. It reminded me a lot of The Martian (well, I’ve only seen the movie, but it feels like the same kind of protagonist). This is sci-fi that doesn’t try to be overly philosophical or groundbreaking; it just wants to entertain you and make everything feel like it could be possible.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the science, Andy Weir has an impressive ability to explain complex concepts without making them feel heavy. It’s not hard sci-fi in the traditional sense, but there’s enough technical detail to make everything seem realistic. From the problem threatening humanity to the space travel solutions and the way the protagonist overcomes each obstacle, everything is packed with scientific explanations that make the story feel believable without making you feel like you’re sitting in a physics lecture.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There’s also an interesting twist in the plot that I don’t want to spoil too much, but it involves the discovery of a new form of intelligent life. What I liked is that it’s not the typical humanoid alien you can communicate with right away. The way that relationship develops is one of the book’s strongest aspects and adds an extra layer of originality.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If I had to mention something that might not work for everyone, it’s the protagonist. Not everyone is going to like him. He has a lot of energy, a lot of internal monologue, and a sense of humor that might feel repetitive if you don’t click with it. It didn’t bother me, but I can see how it might not be for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I don’t think the book has a particularly deep message. It’s not one of those stories that make you question existence or rethink the future of humanity. It does touch on themes like global cooperation, the importance of science, and sacrifice, but never in a very profound way. And I don’t think that’s a problem. Not every book has to change your life—some just need to be fun.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As for who I’d recommend it to, I think it’s perfect for someone who enjoys sci-fi but doesn’t want to dive into something as dense as Foundation or Dune. It’s a fast-paced, easy-to-read book with solid science and a gripping rhythm. If you like stories that include a lot of scientific explanations but don’t feel like a technical manual, this book is for you. On the other hand, if you find detailed scientific explanations boring, this might not be the best choice, since Andy Weir dedicates a lot of space to breaking down how things work.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I’d definitely read it again. Not because it has hidden mysteries that require a second read, but simply because I enjoyed it enough to want to relive the experience in a few years when I’ve forgotten some details. It also made me want to read &lt;em&gt;The Martian&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Artemis&lt;/em&gt;, so those are probably next on my list.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
